Something strange is happening right now
in Central Asia that has so far escaped
most of the world's attention. The
Caspian Sea is the largest inland body
of water that can be found anywhere in
the world. Placed over the United
States, it would stretch roughly from
Los Angeles in the south all the way up
into Oregon and Idaho in the north. With
no natural connection to the rest of the
world's oceans, the Caspian is
technically the world's largest lake
both by surface area and by volume. It
is bordered by five countries, Russia,
Kazakhstan, Turkmenistan, Azerbaijan,
and Iran. And tragically, the Caspian
Sea is rapidly collapsing to the point
where in just a few decades from now,
it'll probably be completely
unrecognizable from today. Based on
multiple recent scientific studies,
including one published in the journal
Nature in 2020 by researchers from the
University of Bremen and Utrecht
University, the Caspian Sea stands to
decline by between 9 m and 18 m by the
end of the 21st century. With a 9 m
decline taking place under a medium
emission scenario and the more
catastrophic 18 m decline taking place
under a high emission scenario. In more
straightforward terms, a 9 m decline in
the water level of the Caspian Sea from
today will translate into a net loss of
23% of the Caspian Sea's current surface
area. While the greater 18 m decline
will result in a net loss of 34% of it.
Either way, it's likely that by the end
of the century, an area roughly the size
of Portugal will dry up and become new
land out of the Caspian Sea, which will
change the world map and global
geography substantially within many of
our own lifetimes. And most alarmingly
of all, the northern parts of the
Caspian Sea might disappear within just
the next couple of decades by 2050.
[music]
You see, the Caspian Sea can be broadly
divided between three different
geographic sub-basins, a northern,
center, and southern basin. And the
depths of water between all of these
basins is radically different. The
southern basin is the deepest of all
with depths reaching more than a full
kilometer, approaching truly oceanic
depths.
>> [music]
>> The center basin is very deep as well
with depths reaching as deep as 788 m.
While by comparison, the northern basin
is extremely extremely shallow. The
northern basin only has a mean depth of
just 5 m. And so despite making up
roughly 1/3 of the Caspian Sea's total
surface area, the northern basin only
accounts for about 1% of the Sea's total
water volume since it's so insanely
shallow by comparison. As a result, the
declining sea levels within the Caspian
will overwhelmingly negatively affect
the northern basin of the Caspian Sea
first bordering Kazakhstan and Russia
along with the shallow Kara-Bogaz Gol
inlet that's fully enclosed within
Turkmenistan.
Even under the 9 m sea level loss
scenario, which might happen by 2050,
most of the shallower northern Caspian
Sea will be lost. While even greater
losses will happen all around the sea
under the 18 m loss scenario.
Interestingly, the projected loss of sea
level within the Caspian across the 21st
century will be the opposite of the
projected gains in sea level happening
across the rest of the world's oceans.
And it's appearing to be a hauntingly
similar scenario to what happened to the
nearby Aral Sea last century, which
itself used to be the third largest lake
in the world before Soviet-era
mismanagement led to its nearly complete
and irreversible collapse by the early
2000s. The larger Caspian Sea might now
be heading in a disturbingly similar
direction and there were many reasons
why.
First of all, it's important to note
that the Caspian Sea has experienced a
very long previous history of both rapid
decline and rapid growth. Over the past
40,000 years, the Caspian Sea's surface
areas routinely expanded and contracted
again with the climate. Like during the
last glacial period when cooler
temperatures resulted in a much lower
evaporation rate. But as the world
warmed and the Eurasian glaciers melted,
depriving the Caspian of a major water
source and shifted more or less into its
current form at the start of recorded
human history. Even afterwards though,
the Caspian would experience huge shifts
in water levels of between 7 and 10 m in
growth or decline over a century or
longer periods. And by the start of the
20th century, we begin having highly
reliable scientific data to actually go
off of. Collected by researchers from
across the Caspian Sea region and
published in a study in Nature in 2025,
measurements of the Caspian Sea's water
level since 1900 show an interesting
pattern. Because the Caspian Sea is very
low beneath the global mean sea level,
the measurements on the x-axis here are
indexed against global mean sea level,
which is why they're all negative. In
other words, at the start of the 20th
century, the Caspian Sea level was
approximately -25.8 m below global mean
sea level. It then decreased by around 2
m over decades until it stabilized in
the 1950s and 60s, before it then began
to decrease rapidly again across the
1970s, reaching its lowest ever point in
the past century in 1977 at -29 m.
Subsequent interventions by the Soviet
Union and a shifting climate actually
managed to curb the trend, and the
Caspian then regained about 2 m of water
level over the next couple of decades by
1995.
But since then, the Caspian has returned
back to a near constant three-decade
long downward trend again, as measured
by NASA's satellite data seen here in
the shallow northeastern corner of the
sea by Kazakhstan. Since 1996, the
Caspian Sea has declined back to -28 m
below the global mean sea level, nearly
as low as the lowest it got in the late
1970s.
In other words, since the 1990s, the
Caspian has already lost approximately
23,858
sq km of its surface area, almost all of
which was lost in the shallow
northeastern sector of the sea. And the
reasons why it's been shrinking again in
our modern era are rather
straightforward. You see, as a fully
enclosed landlocked sea, the Caspian
Sea's water level is defined by the
balance between three interconnected
factors: water inflow rates through
rivers, water inflow rates through
precipitation, and water outflow rates
through evaporation. Approximately 130
rivers flow into the Caspian Sea, which
provide it with incoming fresh water,
but the vast majority of it all just
comes through a single one of them, the
Volga. The Volga is the longest river in
Europe, and with its delta in the
northern Caspian, more than 80% of the
water inflow to the Caspian through
rivers comes through it alone. However,
the amount of water reaching the Caspian
through the Volga has been in a state of
steady decline for decades now.
According to a 2026 peer-reviewed study
published by the American Geophysical
Union, the volume of water discharged
through the Volga into the Caspian has
declined from an average of about 253
cubic kilometers per year between 1991
and 2005 to about 231 cubic kilometers
per year between 2006 and 2020, a
reduction in flow of about 12%.
There's been a lot of speculation and
accusations that this decline is the
fault of Soviet and Russian construction
of dams along the Volga, but the problem
with that line of reasoning is that no
additional dams have been built along
the Volga since the 1980s. Well, the
same study I just mentioned also
concluded that the decline in the
Volga's flow can be attributed entirely
to a decline in precipitation alone.
Regardless of the cause, the primary
source of river inflow into the Caspian
Sea has become increasingly restricted
since the mid-1990s.
At the same time as climate change is
also increasing evaporation within the
sea itself as well. Between 1979 and
2015, the average annual surface air
temperature over the Caspian measurably
increased by around 1° C,
which has substantially increased the
rate of evaporation That's happening
within the Caspian. In fact, the same
2026 study published by the American
Geophysical Union concluded that as much
as 40% of the Caspian Sea's water volume
loss since 2000 can be attributed to
this increase in evaporation rate alone.
While most of the remaining loss can be
attributed to the reduction in river
inflow through the Volga and other
rivers. Thus, if the world continues
warming through the 21st century, which
is likely, the evaporation rate will
likely continue increasing while the
inflow rates through rivers will also
likely continue decreasing. And that's
why the Caspian Sea is projected to
decline by somewhere between 9 and 18 m
by the end of the century, depending on
whether or not we end up in a medium or
a high emission scenario. And the
various implications of that decline
over the next few decades are going to
be very bad for everyone who lives
around the sea. The almost complete loss
of the northern basin of the Caspian Sea
will result in enormous environmental
and ecological damage. The Caspian Sea
serves as a habitat for hundreds of
endemic and migratory species that could
face cascading pressures towards
extinction. The shallower waters in the
north of the Caspian serve as a breeding
and spawning grounds for many of the
sea's fish species, including the
endangered sturgeons that made up the
backbone of the caviar industries in
both Iran and Russia. The loss of those
shallower waters will therefore put even
further extinctionary pressures on the
Caspian sturgeon population. While it'll
be very bad news for the Caspian Sea's
most famous endemic animal as well, the
Caspian seal. Already classified as
endangered, the Caspian seal only exists
within the Caspian Sea. During the
winter season, the shallower northern
reaches of the Caspian Sea will freeze
over with ice, which the Caspian seals
always gather at and use for their
breeding and pupping grounds. However,
even with the lower 9-m projected
decline in the Caspian Sea level,
virtually all of this annual winter sea
ice cover will become lost. And there's
no obvious way that the Caspian Sea
would be able to adapt and survive
afterwards with this complete collapse
of their breeding grounds. And if all
that weren't bad enough, the economic
consequences of the shrinking sea will
be devastating as well. The Caspian Sea
is a major component of the global oil
and gas industry. Roughly 3% of the
world's oil reserves and 4% of the
world's natural gas reserves exist
within and around the sea. While most of
the major oil fields exist in the
northern basin nearby to Kazakhstan,
including the offshore Kashagan field,
the single largest oil field discovered
anywhere in the world in the past 30
years. Tens of billions of dollars from
Kazakhstan and various foreign oil
companies have been invested into
developing and exploiting the Kashagan
field with offshore infrastructures
since it was discovered in 2000. All of
the oil production at Kashagan currently
relies on this offshore infrastructure
and ship-based logistics since it's
currently, you know, surrounded by
water. But in the event of even a 9-m
reduction in the Caspian Sea levels,
Kashagan will become completely
landlocked, which might make the entire
project obsolete and devastate
Kazakhstan's economy. Additionally, the
retreating sea will make docking for
ships increasingly difficult in critical
northeastern Caspian Sea ports like
Aktau and Kuryk in Kazakhstan and
Astrakhan and Makhachkala in Russia,
that will find themselves ever further
away from the new shoreline.
Based on data collected by yet another
scientific study published in Nature in
April of 2025, more than a third of all
the measured industrial infrastructure
facilities around the Caspian, including
oil refineries, gas processing plants,
and ports, will find themselves more
than 5 km away from the Caspian's new
shoreline from where they are today by
the end of the century. Azerbaijan's
largest city and capital, Baku, could
find itself more than a kilometer away
from the new shoreline from where it is
today. Turkmenbashi in Turkmenistan
could end up about 16 km away from the
new sea, while Logan in Russia could
wind up more than 120 km away from the
new coastline. The Caspian Sea has no
natural path out to the world's oceans,
but it does have an artificial one in
the form of the Volga-Don Canal in
Russia, which was opened back in the
1950s and connects the Volga River and
the Don River at their closest points,
which is what enables continuous
navigation across them between the
Caspian and Black Seas. This route
enables countries around the Caspian
that would otherwise be landlocked, like
Azerbaijan, Turkmenistan, and
Kazakhstan, their only meaningful access
to the global ocean and global maritime
trade. However, a collapse in the water
levels of the Caspian Sea will
inevitably result in the lowering of
water levels within the Volga River as
well. That means that ships moving
through the Volga and through the
Volga-Don Canal will have to become
smaller, which will critically
compromise both maritime trade and naval
access for Caspian Sea states like
Azerbaijan, Turkmenistan, and
Kazakhstan.
If all of this comes to pass, it'll also
have critical implications for the
so-called Middle Corridor, the emerging
major trade route between China and
Europe that bypasses major Western
geopolitical foes like Russia and Iran
by running across the Caspia. In order
for the Middle Corridor to properly
function, goods from China cross
Kazakhstan by rail to the port of Aktau,
where they board cargo vessels for
transit across the Caspian to Baku in
Azerbaijan, where they continue onwards
on rail towards Europe. But, with the
sea receding away from both Aktau and
Baku in the more severe projections,
it's unclear how viable this route may
actually be in the long term when
compared to the alternative routes going
through Russia in the north or through
Iran in the south. Going in the other
direction from north to south, it's also
almost certain that the great reduction
in the Caspian Sea level in the north
will hinder trade between Iran and
Russia, too. And the transformation of
the surface area of the Caspian will
also have major geopolitical and border
ramifications, as well. The baseline of
the sea, what determines the territorial
scope of maritime boundaries, will
drastically change with the declining
sea levels, which will result in a
shifting of maritime borders across the
sea that will have to become negotiated
between all five states that surround
it. And additionally, there will be the
question of who will control the newly
revealed land. By the end of the 21st
century, there could be an amount of
dried-up land in the Caspian equivalent
to the size of Portugal. But virtually
all of that land will likely be mostly
useless. It will quickly transform into
either desert or steppe. And then
there's the problem that the Caspian Sea
is heavily polluted, too, from its
history of oil and gas extraction,
shipping, and industrial and sewage
dumping from all of the states that
surround it. As a result, the dried-up
land in the Caspian is likely to be
heavily contaminated by pollutants,
which will make it virtually worthless
for agriculture. And it'll probably be
even worse than useless, because much
like what happened with the dried-up
lake bed of the Aral Sea, winds blowing
across this region will carry all of
that newly exposed toxic dust across the
region that'll wreck the local air
quality. As the drying up of the Caspian
results in economic resources like fish
and oil and gas getting more difficult
to exploit, results in ports and
maritime access getting more difficult
to utilize, and results in a worsening
environmental quality with a likely
increase in toxic dust storms, what will
end up happening to the roughly 15
million people who currently live around
the sea? Many of them will likely pack
up their bags and move somewhere else as
climate refugees, similar to what
happened around the Aral Sea after it
collapsed in the 1990s and in
And again, even if humanity is
successful at curbing our global
emissions, many of the worst
consequences, including the 9-m sea
level decline within the Caspian, is
still likely inevitable, no matter what
happens. Which means that nearly a
quarter of the sea will likely not exist
within only a couple of decades from
now. All we can do is to try and curb
our emissions to save the sea from its
even more catastrophic scenario of an
18-m decline or 34% surface area decline
by 2100.
And only time will tell if we manage to
be successful with that or not.
Over the past few months, the Caspian
Sea has also emerged as a major front in
both the Russia-Ukraine War and the
US-Iran War. Iran has sent drones and
arms to Russia aboard ships transiting
across the Caspian. And after the US
Navy began blockading Iran's oceanic
access, the Caspian became the critical
logistics lifeline for Iran, since they
could at least continue trading with
Russia across it. During my research for
videos that concern these wars, it
always becomes clear that the mainstream
news's portrayal of what's going on are
often pretty skewed and incomplete.
There's always an enormous, overwhelming
amount of coverage of conflicts like
Iran, but in the fog of war and rampant
propaganda coming from both sides, it's
always hard to know what's legitimately
useful information versus incomplete
facts trying to push a politicized
narrative. As I was producing this video
about the Caspian Sea, the US and Iran
met in neutral Switzerland for
negotiations on a final peace deal.
Left-leaning platforms framed these
talks as historic peacemaking that
stressed progress, while casting Trump's
threats as the primary destabilizing
force and Iran's pause as a protest.
While right-leaning platforms flipped
that lens by using words like
unprecedented, hardline, and leverage to
portray Iran as strategic, suspicious,
and bargain-driven, with Lebanon and
sanctions as the real dividing lines.
And that's why I found my sponsor,
Ground News, to be such a crucial tool
while writing many of my videos. I've
partnered with them since 2023, and this
is why. Almost 340 sources covered the
US-Iran negotiations in Switzerland
story, and when I looked on Ground News,
I was able to quickly see how each news
outlet framed the story. Ground News is
an app and website that aggregates
coverage of particular news stories,
sources them based on the political
alignment of the publisher, and then
allows you to compare the way narratives
differ between the sides of the
political spectrum. I know that I
personally tend to consume news sources
that align with my own political bias,
but then even these sources can kind of
confirm my biases by characterizing
politicized stories in a particular way.
>> [music]
>> So, I find Ground News helps a lot when
figuring out what's an objective truth
versus a biased narrative. I also love
that they display the ownership for each
publication, and especially these days,
it's becoming more and more clear how
that can influence what publications
portray as the
And then another feature I use is the
blind spot feed, which shows you stories
that sources on one side of the
political spectrum are talking about. I
think it's extremely fascinating to see
what certain groups of people think is
top news, while others don't even think
about at all. And not only is this
really interesting, but actually really
meaningful. A recent study from Duke
University on polarization in media
found that exposure to news blind spots
can moderate political positions and
reduce polarization. Ground News is a
fully independent, subscriber-funded
for people who want to question the
narrative. So, if that sounds like you,
you can get 40% off unlimited access to
Advantage Plan, the same one that I use,
by scanning the QR code here on your
screen, or by heading to the link that's
down below in the description at
ground.news/reallifelore.
Signing up really helps support my
channel at the same time, so thanks in
advance if you do. And as always, thank
you so much for watching, as well.